The next cast we're going to learn is the overhead cast.
The overhead cast has two directions.
It has a back direction and a forward direction.
The back direction is the hardest to learn because it's really difficult for us to essentially learn to make our muscles cast backwards and then go forward.
So the overhead cast is used when you have lots of room behind you to make a forward cast and a back cast and you're not limited with back cast room like we did with the Roll cast.
Notice how this is raised up?
And then all we do is drop our elbow down.
Drop.
And there is our completed overhead cast.
Now that you've learned the movements, we are going to make the cast with the rod, reel, and line.
It's always best to start out with a short amount of line and learn to cast it well before you go for the gusto and the distance.
So, we're going to do just like we did with the Roll cast.
We're going to start with our tip down, we're going to lift, we're going to slide back like this.
Now, notice how we flick out rod tip up?
Flick up, there, and there's our cast.
So, as you've noticed as I brought this rod up, my head actually followed my hand and I went up to my rod tip to see the line and I came forward.
When you're learning this it is really crucial that you watch the timing of the rod and the line as it works.